<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wojciech Francuzik on Wojciech Francuzik</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wojciech Francuzik on Wojciech Francuzik</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC-BY 4.0; 2017 Wojciech Francuzik</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducibility in research</title>
      <link>/talk/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 19:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Further details will be availible here&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors and treatment of refractory anaphylaxis - a review of case reports</title>
      <link>/publication/refractoryana/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 16:43:37 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/refractoryana/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Factors increasing the risk for a severe reaction in anaphylaxis: An analysis of Data from The European Anaphylaxis Registry</title>
      <link>/publication/worm2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/worm2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Propionibacterium acnes Abundance Correlates Inversely with Staphylococcus aureus. Data from Atopic Dermatitis Skin Microbiome</title>
      <link>/publication/francuzik2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/francuzik2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluate optical density to get concentrations of your ELISA</title>
      <link>/post/evaluate-optical-density-to-get-concentrations-of-your-elisa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/evaluate-optical-density-to-get-concentrations-of-your-elisa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I was doing a quick ELISA and realized that the reader was old and produced the results in PDF only. This poses multiple problems as they need to be manually rewritten to a file and post-processed later. Additionally the optical density measurments in my software are automatically calculated into concentration based on some shady functions which I never understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to change this and learn this and that about analysing ELISA results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first thing that got me - OPTICAL DENSITY measurments were unaffected by the analysis type. So I had to use these raw values as my starting point. Extracting these was a matter of using Rpoppler package to extract pdf into txt and than using som gsub commands to get the exact values that I needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the manual of my elisa recommended using the 4 parameter models and I had to look for a function which could facilitate this. &lt;code&gt;drc&lt;/code&gt; package has this covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly wrote a function based on a post on research gate, and was able to get my results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#&#39; Calculate the concentration of a substrate from a known OPTICAL DENSITY
#&#39;
#&#39; This function will give a calculated concentration of a subsance in 96 well 
#&#39; plate given the optical density from a plate reader.
#&#39; 
#&#39; @param OD Optical density of the STANDARD DILUTION [numeric vector]
#&#39; @param conc KNOWN concentrations of the standard dilution [numeric vector]
#&#39; @param OD_sample Optical densities of samples [named vector]
#&#39; @return A data frame with OD, log fitted values and calculated concentrations
#&#39;  of the samples and a plot with a standard curve standard and blue samples
#&#39; @author Wojciech Francuzik
#&#39; @details This function is useful when working with old plate readers. It uses 
#&#39; the FOUR PARAMETER CURVE to fit the model to your standards. 
#&#39; @export elisa4ll

elisa4ll &amp;lt;- function(OD,conc,OD_sample){
    require(drc)
logconc &amp;lt;-log10(conc)# log10 from conc
stdcrvdata &amp;lt;- data.frame(OD,conc,logconc)
fit&amp;lt;-drm(formula = OD ~ conc , data = stdcrvdata, fct = LL.4())
samples &amp;lt;- data.frame(OD=OD_sample)# data from mesurments
samples$loganswer&amp;lt;- fit$coefficients[4]*
    (((-1* fit$coefficients[3]+samples$OD)/
          (fit$coefficients[2]-samples$OD))^(1/ fit$coefficients[1]))
samples$conc &amp;lt;- 10^samples$loganswer
plot(fit)
lines(samples$loganswer,samples$OD, type=&amp;quot;points&amp;quot;, col=&amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;) 
return(samples)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is available in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wolass/rlabbook&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;rlabbook package&lt;/a&gt; (which is a slow WIP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically if you provide this function with a set of OD reads from samples and standard curve along with the known concentrations of the standard dilution - you should get your concentrations calculated accordingly. It also plots a nice plot. There could be a tone more features but is it necessary?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this helps someone!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R package as a reproducible piece of scientific communication</title>
      <link>/post/r-package-as-a-reproducible-piece-of-scientific-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/r-package-as-a-reproducible-piece-of-scientific-communication/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Why do scientists still use journal articles as main form of sharing their research? The paper publication has been with the academics since ages and it surely does need an update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variety of outputs we have to offer ar modern scientists had dramatically evolved and contains multigiabyte databases along with high quality images, and simple text output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We therefore need a modern medium which allows sharing such sophisticated data and paper simply is not suited for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to answer my own question - it all lies in incentives. Scientist publish in paper academic journals because they are rewarded with “Impact Factor points”. These are then exchanged (being a form of evaluation how good a certain group of researchers is) for more funding for science, staff, consumables, rooms. Essentially all resources are divided between reaserch groups according to this extreamly biased benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the problem of providing high quality proofs to scientific questions is not well addressed, by following these incentives because it just doesn’t calculate to put extra effort for ensuring quality research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But scientists aside from being calculated people are sometimes also ethical. One example of this is sharing scientific discoveries openly and not bothering with impact points. Prof. Ben Marvic is such a guy! Have a look at his repos on github. Especially &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/benmarwick/researchcompendium&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; got my attention. Researchcompendium is a package - template for science projects that adds a lot of structure for reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this form of scientific communication has the chance to be equal to journal publications?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I suggest to try the package! I will and my experience will be covered in next posts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epineural Sheath Jacket as a New Surgical Technique for Neuroma Prevention in the Rat Sciatic Nerve Model</title>
      <link>/publication/siemionow2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/siemionow2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serum levels of 9-alpha, 11-beta-PGF2 and apolipoprotein A1 achieve high predictive power as biomarkers of anaphylaxis</title>
      <link>/publication/wittenberg2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/wittenberg2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The influence of rifaximin on diverticulitis rate and quality of life in patients with diverticulosis</title>
      <link>/publication/rifaximin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/rifaximin/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Botulinum Toxin Injection for Treatment of Chronic Anal Fissure: Is There Any Dose-Dependent Efficiency? A Meta-Analysis</title>
      <link>/publication/4adam2016botulinum/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/4adam2016botulinum/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laser therapies for onychomycosis--critical evaluation of methods and effectiveness</title>
      <link>/publication/francuzik2016laser/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/francuzik2016laser/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impact of sex on anaphylaxis severity—data from the Anaphylaxis Registry</title>
      <link>/publication/test/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 16:43:37 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/test/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data from the anaphylaxis registry of the German-speaking countries</title>
      <link>/publication/2worm2015data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2worm2015data/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical and economic benefit of negative pressure wound therapy in treatment of the open abdomen</title>
      <link>/publication/6banasiewicz2014clinical/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/6banasiewicz2014clinical/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improvement of Therapy Outcomes after Negative Pressure Wound Therapy in a Patient with Acne inversa</title>
      <link>/publication/5francuzik2014improvement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/5francuzik2014improvement/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
