<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wojciech Francuzik on Wojciech Francuzik</title>
    <link>https://wolass.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wojciech Francuzik on Wojciech Francuzik</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC-BY 4.0; 2017 Wojciech Francuzik</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Anaphylaxis</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/project/anaphylaxis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/project/anaphylaxis/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Anaphylaxis Registry is a uniqe database, that gathers anaphylaxis cases along with high quality clinical data. It is maintained by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anaphylaxie.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NORA e.V.&lt;/a&gt;.
I&amp;rsquo;m lucky to be working on this challenging dataset as a data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-job-in-the-project&#34;&gt;My job in the project&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work on the European Anaphylaxis Registry started in 2015. I first looked into the sex differences in anaphylaxis severity. Next, I was investigating the influence of aggrevating factors on the severity of anaphylaxis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-i-have-learned&#34;&gt;What I have learned&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project was a demanding and complex task which required me to incorporate new tools int daily practice. I had to reorganise my analytic workflow to use GIT daily, registering all changes made to the files. Also collaboration with tem members who preferred to work with Word files posed a challenge. Nevertheless, I managed to use R to create a reproducible paper written entirly in R and with the use of &amp;ldquo;knitr&amp;rdquo; package convert it into final word documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have learned how to work with bibliographies in R, how to divide analysis and reports into separate files which than can be used to produce the final manuscript. During this project I had to start writing my own package with helper functions around the logistic regression outputs and I have seen the problems of scalability, that were resolvesd by over 50 custom R scripts, to manage the big data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills-learned&#34;&gt;Skills learned:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logistic regression analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comparing logistic regression models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Odds ratios and relative risks differences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code externalization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;ggplot&lt;/em&gt; perfection to produce publication ready figures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meta-science-conclusions&#34;&gt;Meta-science conclusions:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is possible to collaborate on a manuscript with multiple authors on a paper written directly in &lt;em&gt;knitr&lt;/em&gt;, but it requires that all changes be introduced to the source files each time what can be a daunting task. 2. Using GIT is essential not to get lost in along the way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a strict stucture for the analysis for future projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analysis and manuscript write-ups need a strictly defined file structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mimimizing code snippets in the manuscript file increases the readability of the file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All functions should be in separate files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wrapping a paper into a &lt;em&gt;R package&lt;/em&gt; might be a good idea for future projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NPWT</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/project/npwt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/project/npwt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My work on Negative Pressure Wound Therapy use in Dermatology started in 2014. I first descibed a case report where NPWT was used after surgical procedure in a patient with acne inversa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, I was intersted in following up on how to cut costs of NPWT in hospital setting to make this techniqe more easily availible. This reaseach is ongoing and I will share more details in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Init lab</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/post/init-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/post/init-lab/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my initial post. Communication in science is changing not so rapidly as it should. Use of new tools and methods may drive change in the way we communicate experiment results.
I have been using R and Rstudio extensively since last 4 years. It has proven exeptionally well suited for making science and my latest attempts at producing full manuscripts in RStudio were suprisingly successful. This lead me to investigating new forms of scientific communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this site is to a) order my knowledge and programming skills, b) make me practice clear communication with the readers, c) promote Open Science and d) serve as an Open Lab Notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be using the &amp;lsquo;blogdown&amp;rsquo; package by Yihui Xie to serve this site. My ideas and data will be shared openly using the CC-BY 4.0 License. There is no funding for this site, and the data I share here are my own. To host the page I&amp;rsquo;ll use github and AWS for the domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far using blogdown was a blast and it works great. I have a lot of topics to cover in the following posts. This will be documenting my experience how to set up an academig website using blogdown and github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setup&#34;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete instructions to get you started right away are written &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here by the author of the blogdown package&lt;/a&gt;. If you want th get right to business &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/workflow.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;try this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: setting up the blogdown and hugo and previewing locally takes no more than 5 minutes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time consumig part is getting all the personal details and the list of publications into the file structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really love that everything here is written in markdown!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;academic-details&#34;&gt;Academic details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose the academic template because it ideally answers my needs. You need to add some links to the most used account in the configuration file: Research gate, Impactstory, twitter links and so on. It takes a couple of hours. To represent your current CV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;publishing&#34;&gt;Publishing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already had a domain and used the github hosting service. So for me this did not make a difference, but setting these up is also not that hard. Details are in the Blogdown&amp;rsquo;s manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;discussion&#34;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could this type of content be the future of scientific communication? Or are we bound to paper journals and good ol&amp;rsquo; Impact Factor?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epineural Sheath Jacket as a New Surgical Technique for Neuroma Prevention in the Rat Sciatic Nerve Model.</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/publication/neural-sheath/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/publication/neural-sheath/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More detail can easily be written here using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serum levels of 9α, 11β‐PGF2 and apolipoprotein A1 achieve high predictive power as biomarkers of anaphylaxis</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/publication/serum-ana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/publication/serum-ana/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Microbiome in Skin Diseases: looking back to move forward</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/talk/indercos2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/talk/indercos2/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The influence of rifaximin on diverticulitis rate and quality of life in patients with diverticulosis.</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/publication/rifaximin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/publication/rifaximin/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Botulinum Toxin Injection for Treatment of Chronic Anal Fissure: Is There Any Dose-Dependent Efficiency? A Meta-Analysis</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/publication/botox-af/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/publication/botox-af/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical and Economic Benefit of Negative Pressure Wound Therapy in Treatment of the Open Abdomen</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/publication/oa-npwt/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/publication/oa-npwt/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laser therapies for onychomycosis – critical evaluation of methods and effectiveness</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/publication/laser-onychomycosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/publication/laser-onychomycosis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge about ultraviolet radiation hazards and tanning behavior of cosmetology and medical students</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/publication/radiation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/publication/radiation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data from the anaphylaxis registry of the German-speaking countries</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/publication/german-ana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/publication/german-ana/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impact of sex on anaphylaxis severity—data from the Anaphylaxis Registry</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/publication/sex-ana/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/publication/sex-ana/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improvement of Therapy Outcomes after Negative Pressure Wound Therapy in a Patient with Acne inversa.</title>
      <link>https://wolass.github.io/publication/acneinversa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wolass.github.io/publication/acneinversa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
