<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Scientific Communication on Wojciech Francuzik</title>
    <link>/categories/scientific-communication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Scientific Communication on Wojciech Francuzik</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>CC-BY 4.0; 2017 Wojciech Francuzik</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/scientific-communication/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>R package as a reproducible piece of scientific communication</title>
      <link>/post/r-package-as-a-reproducible-piece-of-scientific-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/r-package-as-a-reproducible-piece-of-scientific-communication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why do scientists still use journal articles as main form of sharing their research? The paper publication has been with the academics since ages and it surely does need an update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variety of outputs we have to offer ar modern scientists had dramatically evolved and contains multigiabyte databases along with high quality images, and simple text output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We therefore need a modern medium which allows sharing such sophisticated data and paper simply is not suited for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to answer my own question - it all lies in incentives. Scientist publish in paper academic journals because they are rewarded with “Impact Factor points”. These are then exchanged (being a form of evaluation how good a certain group of researchers is) for more funding for science, staff, consumables, rooms. Essentially all resources are divided between reaserch groups according to this extreamly biased benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the problem of providing high quality proofs to scientific questions is not well addressed, by following these incentives because it just doesn’t calculate to put extra effort for ensuring quality research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But scientists aside from being calculated people are sometimes also ethical. One example of this is sharing scientific discoveries openly and not bothering with impact points. Prof. Ben Marvic is such a guy! Have a look at his repos on github. Especially &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/benmarwick/researchcompendium&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; got my attention. Researchcompendium is a package - template for science projects that adds a lot of structure for reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this form of scientific communication has the chance to be equal to journal publications?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I suggest to try the package! I will and my experience will be covered in next posts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Init lab</title>
      <link>/post/init-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/init-lab/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my initial post. Communication in science is changing not so rapidly as it should. Use of new tools and methods may drive change in the way we communicate experiment results.
I have been using R and Rstudio extensively since last 4 years. It has proven exeptionally well suited for making science and my latest attempts at producing full manuscripts in RStudio were suprisingly successful. This lead me to investigating new forms of scientific communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this site is to a) order my knowledge and programming skills, b) make me practice clear communication with the readers, c) promote Open Science and d) serve as an Open Lab Notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be using the &amp;lsquo;blogdown&amp;rsquo; package by Yihui Xie to serve this site. My ideas and data will be shared openly using the CC-BY 4.0 License. There is no funding for this site, and the data I share here are my own. To host the page I&amp;rsquo;ll use github and AWS for the domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far using blogdown was a blast and it works great. I have a lot of topics to cover in the following posts. This will be documenting my experience how to set up an academig website using blogdown and github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setup&#34;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete instructions to get you started right away are written &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here by the author of the blogdown package&lt;/a&gt;. If you want th get right to business &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/workflow.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;try this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: setting up the blogdown and hugo and previewing locally takes no more than 5 minutes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time consumig part is getting all the personal details and the list of publications into the file structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really love that everything here is written in markdown!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;academic-details&#34;&gt;Academic details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose the academic template because it ideally answers my needs. You need to add some links to the most used account in the configuration file: Research gate, Impactstory, twitter links and so on. It takes a couple of hours. To represent your current CV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;publishing&#34;&gt;Publishing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already had a domain and used the github hosting service. So for me this did not make a difference, but setting these up is also not that hard. Details are in the Blogdown&amp;rsquo;s manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;discussion&#34;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could this type of content be the future of scientific communication? Or are we bound to paper journals and good ol&amp;rsquo; Impact Factor?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
